welcome back to the backstory
i'm former cia officer john kiriakou in
our last half hour
we are happy to welcome journalist and
political analyst caleb maupin
caleb is one of the best informed people
out there and we have a lot to talk
about
caleb welcome back to the show sure glad
to be here
as always well we're glad to have you
there's so much that i want to ask you
but but the first thing i want to ask is
uh
is something that's kind of funny so um
i googled you the other day
i just was curious to see what you were
working on and
i was amused to see you identified as a
radical
are you a radical what does that mean
well i think the
roots of the term radical it simply
means that you want to get to the root
of the problem right so i guess in that
sense
that i see the roots of the problem in
the world today as being our global
capitalist system the rule of the world
by a few big
multinational corporations who continue
to
try and keep the world poor and make the
world poorer in order to secure their
profits and make themselves wealthier um
i guess if i see that
overall systemic problem as behind many
of the
individual situations that we discussed
in radio interviews i guess in that
sense i'm radical
um but it's interesting that i'm
identified that way i've been called
many things
uh in my life uh i guess radical is
certainly one of them
and of all the labels i've been given
it's not one i'm anxious to disown
there you go there you go i like that
well let's start off
with uh with international affairs i
want to ask you
about about something coming out of
sanctions
i was watching one of the sunday morning
talk shows this past weekend and
the guest was talking about uh sanctions
as a soft power weapon that rather than
rather than using hard power and going
to war
over every little issue that sanctions
were very
valuable as as a tool in foreign policy
i disagree strongly with that with that
position
um i think sanctions do nothing but but
hurt
uh average citizens
that sanctions invariably invariably
hit food supplies medicine
clean water everything that people need
to just survive on a day-to-day basis
but but this guy was saying that
sanctions against iran
against russia against china were
working
and that what we've seen is these three
countries
essentially pull together in order to
counter sanctions
give me your thoughts if you don't mind
on sanctions
and on the role of sanctions in u.s
foreign policy and then i want to ask
you specifically about some of these
countries
well sanctions should be called what
they really are which is economic
warfare um it is an attempt to attack a
country
by using economic means rather than
using bombs and tanks and drones and
direct military strikes
and often people think of sanctions as
being are we cut into the profit margins
of some of the elite
businessmen in the country or other of
those who you know do
business in the state sector etc but
they do hit ordinary people in pretty
horrendous ways
uh when i was in iran uh i was served
tea
as i was waiting to give a tv interview
by an airline pilot
uh and this airline pilot had completed
uh he'd gotten his
you know airline pilot's license but
because of these sanctions on iran
iran is able unable to get airplane
parts and uh
their travel and iran is very restricted
and so even though his dream was to
become an airline pilot even though he
had his license and was ready to become
an airline pilot
he was stuck serving tea to guys like me
waiting to do tv interviews uh because
of the sanction however when i went to
ecuador for the world
festival of youth and students back in
uh 2013 i i met
a disabled young man um you know who is
confined to a wheelchair
um because of the genetic condition he
has and if it were not for
the sanctions on cuba that prevents cuba
from
getting uh the the medical supplies it
needs
uh if if those medical supplies were
available he would be cured of this
ailment and he would not be able to not
be forced to be in a wheelchair and that
was definitely heartbreaking to me i
mean sanctions kill people
uh the most blatant example is the
sanctions on iraq during the 1990s
uh during the 1990s uh the united
nations and the world health
organization
said that the sanctions uh you know many
people resigned there were a number of
world health organization officials who
resigned the sanctions on iraq
resulted in an estimate of 1.2 million
deaths
half of them children under 12. the word
genocide was used by officials who
resigned
what the united states did by preventing
iraq from getting chlorine to treat
their water
and preventing iraq from importing
medicine it resulted in in a
humanitarian catastrophe that claimed
lots of lives so
sanctions are not a laughing matter
people call them soft power but it
effectively it directly affects people's
lives you know people talk about the
economic impact of the lockdown
here in the united states well you know
now i mean think about how the lockdown
has affected people think about the
results of the lockdown
uh you know you can understand how
economic warfare and economic moves can
directly impact people's lives and
that's what that's what economic
sanctions are
yeah and and they're meant to destroy
societies
uh you you raise cuba i think that's a
prime example
we've had sanctions on cuba for for
almost
60 years now or maybe it is 60 years now
uh look at iran we've had sanctions on
iran since 1979.
the iranians could be utterly
self-sufficient if it weren't for
for sanctions they can certainly grow
their own food uh
they have uh they have vast oil reserves
but we don't allow them to do anything
so tell us a little bit about
about this this reporting that iran
russia and china are working together
now
after sanctions we've got sanctions on
all three of these countries which seems
counterproductive and silly to me uh but
what are they doing to work together
well it's quite interesting the
countries all three of them they kind of
are an odd match made in heaven you
would think they are completely
different
right so china that's the communist
party chinese communist party has been
in power since 1949
uh they drastically reshifted their
their foreign policies starting in the
70s and started aligning with the united
states and
their domestic economic policies
drastically shifted in the late 70s with
the reform and opening up
but their ideology is very much marxism
leninism uh
you know they are a you know a communist
government
they you know have essentially planned
economy five-year economic plans
state-owned industries and they're a
manufacturing country largely
they make half the world steel uh they
have the world's largest
telecommunications manufacturer they
make the majority of the world's copper
the majority of the world's solar panels
russia on the other hand you know at one
point yes you had the soviet union
in the 90s you had the fall of the
soviet union which was an economic
catastrophe
but you know starting in 1999 you had
the rise of vladimir putin and a kind of
restructuring of russia's economy to
once again be centered around the state
um at this point russia is an energy
producing country gazprom and rosneft
two state-controlled energy corporations
uh basically hold up the russian economy
the economy is centered around state
control
over natural resources and the export of
energy um
and it's an energy exporting country i
mean they have a lot of manufacturing
there a lot of steel they have titanium
manufacturing et cetera
but it's largely an economy centered
around energy
iran on the other hand is also uh an
oil-based economy and again
you know uh you know definitely not a
marxist country by any means uh you know
it's a country where
in 1979 you had a religious revolution
and the ayatollahs took power they
overthrew the
the old monarchy that was backed by the
united states the slogan was not
capitalism but
islam neither east nor west a war of
poverty against wealth
and you have a state apparatus that is
you know the islamic revolutionary guard
corps which is the biggest economic
entity in the country
and they control the natural resources
namely petroleum
there's a number of other state
industries state car manufacturing state
steel manufacturing
you have a very big state that kind of
provides for the population
and has kind of a hostile relationship
with business and in a way
all of these countries while they have
different ideologies and different
perspectives you know russia is now very
much you know nationalistic and
christian
orthodox christian and their outlook
china is still espoused as marxism
iran espouses and islamic uh you know
theology shia islam
all of them kind of have this same
overall setup where you have the state
kind of controlling the economy you have
a market sector but a state
basically a state-run economy um and
raising people out of poverty using
state-controlled economic entities to
stimulate
other sections of the economy and uh and
they would all like to get along with
the west i mean they would all love to
get along with the united states they
don't have you know i mean in iran in
the early years yes they were saying
death to america and such but at this
point iran
iran is not seeking you know a hostile
relationship with the united states
neither is china neither is russia
but because of that because these
countries are not wall street's
playground
they've been targeted so as they're
being targeted uh they're starting to do
business with each other
and and they're becoming more dependent
on each other because the sanctions from
the united states uh
cut them off and cut off their ability
to do business with other forces
and you know china as its
state-controlled apparatus of
industrial production expands they need
lots of oil and they need lots of
natural gas
well just so happens russia uh as their
you know as their economy grows and
their state-controlled energy
resources expand they need to sell lots
of oil and lots of natural gas right
what are their basis of economy so
russia and china kind of go together
very very well um you know iran also
needs to sell oil right oil is the basis
of
its economy china needs to buy oil um
you know iran needs more cell phones
right well china
at this point has the world's largest
telecommunications manufacturer the
countries
they kind of all go together it makes
you think about zvignu brzezinski and
his book
the uh the grand chess board where he
talked about the struggle to control
eurasia
and the eurasian hemisphere being kind
of uh kind of
the battle to control the world i think
the nazis made a similar argument they
called it the heartland
um and when hitler invaded russia it was
about trying to seize control of eurasia
but eurasia you know the eurasian world
island or whatever you want to call it
that is kind of a basis for dominating
the world and russia
and china and iran have kicked the
united states and the u.s you know
monopolies and big corporations out of a
big section of the eurasian hemisphere
um and it has asserted its independence
and it's a geopolitical
uh game changer and it's something that
the big bankers and monopolists that
dominate our economy would like to see
reverse
they would like to be in control of
eurasia we've got about uh two minutes
before we have to take a break but i
want to ask you and
there may not even be enough time to to
answer this question
but can you see a situation where
the united states becomes so dependent
on
on sanctions as a foreign policy tool
that we're left behind
that these other countries like russia
china uh
iran and and others go around us and
do business with each other in spite of
uh
our sanctions where they just ignore
them and then we're left in the dust
absolutely i mean there's there are huge
breakthroughs going on in china in terms
of computers
vladimir putin has called for an
international combined effort
around the issue of fusion energy um and
uh yeah i mean i can definitely see the
united states getting locked out i mean
look china is already
in you know trying to basically build up
its response to hollywood
uh you know and and make their own
movies um you know and and
you know and so yeah there's a lot of
developments that we are definitely
getting locked out of
by trying to lock the other countries
out of okay let's take a break we'll
take a short one
we'll come right back and uh let's talk
about afghanistan when we come back
you're listening to the backstory stay
tuned we have a lot more coming up
[Music]
welcome back to the back story i'm john
kiriakou we're having a nice
conversation with caleb maupin
he is a political consultant and
journalist
uh specializing in uh in foreign policy
foreign affairs and i want to ask you
caleb
about this situation in afghanistan it
seems that uh that something
embarrassing was leaked over the last
couple of days and this was a letter
written by the u.s government which
means
the state department in this case um
urging the taliban
and the the afghan government to
cooperate
uh what's this all about and why is it
embarrassing
well i mean as the letter stated uh the
usa is
kind of pushing the afghan government to
enter a
power sharing agreement with the taliban
you'll remember
20 years ago well over 20 years ago when
the united states invaded afghanistan it
did it for the purpose of deposing the
taliban
but now it appears that anthony blinken
is pushing the afghan government to sign
a deal where the taliban would get 50
control over key executive bodies the
taliban's military would be absorbed
into the afghan security forces um and
that's got to be embarrassing for the
united states to you know
to you know have invaded and occupied
afghanistan for over 20 years for the
purpose of fighting the taliban
to just then you know take an agreement
of handing the country back to the
taliban i think that's that's what the
issue there is
yeah i think this is embarrassing
actually i mean
i i was all for the the peace process i
said most americans were all for the
peace process
um that was taking place in doha during
the
the trump administration but it just
seems to me
that the biden administration is giving
up
at least that's what i that's what i
read in this uh
in this letter power sharing is great
but there have to be guarantees
guarantees like rights for women
guarantees like
uh right for education for girls
guarantees like voting rights for
citizens
what we don't want to see is another
coup
by the taliban or a taking of power by
force by the taliban like we saw in the
in the 1990s
whereby you either get with the program
or you're beheaded
that's not what uh what we've been
fighting for for the last
20 years well i have long main things
that i feel like the united states
doesn't really want a stable
afghanistan for the very reasons that we
discussed in our previous segment before
the commercial break
top three geopolitical rivals the united
states iran
russia and china look at a map where is
afghanistan it is
right there in the middle of all three
of them
right uh you've got russia to the north
you've got china to the west
uh and you've got or to the east uh and
then and you've then got iran on you
know to the south of them and
that all three of those countries have
suffered from a big problem
of of terrorist groups operating based
in afghanistan going over their borders
and spreading chaos
of drug gangs and heroin dealers uh you
know operating in afghanistan going in
over their borders
and that keeping afghanistan is kind of
a strategic epicenter of chaos
with you know iran russia and china
having to deal with all the
problems you know flowing over their
borders from an unstable afghanistan
has been a way to to you know covertly
kind of
you know harass these three eurasian
rivals of american power
and to have afghanistan you know right
there in central asia
as you know now afghanistan is the
center of the global heroin trade at
least 50 percent of the world's heroin
comes from afghanistan
right i mean it's copy fields everywhere
uh you know all kinds of terrorist
groups are operating there
um all kinds of weapons are flowing out
of afghanistan from terrorist groups
into the hands of terrorist groups
throughout the region
afghanistan and its instability um and
it's poverty really i mean it's a very
very impoverished country
um has caused lots of problems for the
countries that border it
and three of those countries happen to
be major rivals of the united states now
this power sharing agreement uh if it is
implemented
it may result uh in further further
instability in afghanistan
and that would be you know in the
long-term interest of trying to
destabilize
iran russia and china so it's not
particularly shocking to me
what i do think is interesting is that
uh the taliban
uh you know you talk about their history
they're emerging kind of as a faction
among the folks who fought against the
soviet union in the 1980s
uh you know then in the 90s you have a
coup and
you know they take power and then
they're eradicating drugs
and there's the whole issue where they
wouldn't go along with the pipeline that
the united states wanted and
you know the taliban you know their
geopolitical loyalties seem to drift in
the wind
they will do business with whoever they
think will give them the best deal
um at the end of the day and i think
that that is something the united states
is very aware of that
the taliban is in business for itself it
is a religious
entity uh fanatical but it's not you
know it's not particularly loyal to the
united states it's not particularly
loyal to russia or china or the us's
geopolitical rivals the taliban works
for the taliban and they'll make a deal
with anybody based on what they think is
in their short-term interest
i think that's right and you know i
think that the afghan government
is kowtowing to the taliban right now
because they see the writing on the wall
just this morning
for example the the afghan ministry of
education
uh announced a new um ban
on girls over the age of 12
singing in public so if you are a girl
over the age of 12 you are no longer
allowed to sing in public and if you're
caught singing
you will be jailed we should expect to
see things like that but with that said
i agree with you that the taliban is
loyal to nobody
and if you look historically they never
have been the taliban
leadership was shocked for example in
2001 when we began attacking them
because they made clear that osama bin
laden aside
they had no beef with the united states
right that they were compelled by their
culture
to provide shelter for for al qaeda
because
al qaeda had asked for it and
their culture compelled them to provide
aid to an outsider a foreigner
who requested that aid it's just the way
it's been for
thousands of years and so they argued
that
they had no problem with the united
states they had not
raised arms against the united states
and they couldn't understand why we
wanted to overthrow them and fight them
that if we wanted to fight al qaeda on
their soil that was perfectly fine and
good
but there was no reason for us to
overthrow them and then
overthrow them we did i agree with you
though and it's not just
it's not just the taliban in that region
when i was serving in in pakistan
there were billboards all over the place
in in lahore
in islamabad in peshawar that were
lauding this new bridge called the peace
and friendship bridge
that connected northernmost pakistan
with western china there's this little
teeny tiny strip of land
that constitutes the chinese pakistan
border it's
barely noticeable on a map and they
built a bridge connecting the two
the two countries over a river and i
said to this general
who was my regular point of contact you
guys sure are making a big deal about
this
peace and friendship bridge and very
pointedly he said to me
yes he said the chinese are the only
friends we have in the world who have
never
turned on us and then he looked at me
because god knows we've turned on the
pakistanis over the years
so it's not just afghanistan it's
pakistan it's india to a certain respect
respect it's tajikistan and uzbekistan
you know they'll work with us now but
they don't necessarily trust us and they
certainly don't think we'll be there for
them over the long term
indeed look the best time in afghan
history for women
was the period when afghanistan starting
from 1978 up until
i think 1993. absolutely we had the the
people's democratic republic of
afghanistan
um and the people's democratic party
took power and they
started teaching women to read um they
you know had literacy campaigns in the
countryside they started reforesting the
country uh because the british empire
had cut down a lot of their trees and
they started
you know reforesting parts of the
country that had just been you know
devastated by the british you know
taking all their lumber
and you know they had they had a lot of
you know efforts to try and
industrialize the country now
unfortunately
the people's democratic party was a
marxist-leninist communist
soviet-aligned party
and there was a faction in the people's
democratic party that was
i think you would call them ultra left
or ultra radical
um and they were very hostile to the
peasantry the peasantry of afghanistan
the rural folks
uh anyone who's been there will tell you
how deeply deeply conservative
those folks are i mean i mean islam
religion is the center of their lives
and obviously you know the marxist
leninist party was an
atheist party it had an anti-religious
viewpoint it viewed
religion as primitive and superstitious
and while one faction
of the people's democratic party was
trying to be more sensitive to islam
uh the more radical faction uh you know
uh
continued to be very hostile to the
religious folks
in the countryside and that created an
opening you know for
osama bin laden and you know the united
states aligning with you know wahhabi
forces muslims around the world you know
going to afghanistan to fight the soviet
union
and uh and that's kind of the situation
there um i would say that you know that
bridge that you talked about is very
important because at the end of the day
the only way you're really going to get
stability in afghanistan is with
economic development
as long as people are impoverished and
starving and desperate you're going to
have drug gangs you're going to have
terrorist groups
when people have real economic
opportunity uh when you you know if you
could bring railway through afghanistan
you could have some some factories in
afghanistan that could export products
that could then you know get to the
ocean through
through railway transportation or some
highways um if you look at some of the
plans that have been drawn up you know
with you know iran or china with the
belton road initiative
economic development would bring a
stable afghanistan that's really the
only way you can do it i mean it's an
economic problem fundamentally
this is a part of the world that has
been left behind from industrialization
i mean i mean there's
massive literacy in afghanistan so i
mean i mean
lots of people without running water
without electricity i couldn't agree
more
we've got about three and a half minutes
left and i want to turn to haiti
um haiti is in the throes of
what may be a revolution right now and
it's getting almost
zero coverage in the american press tell
us a little bit about what's happening
in haiti and why it's so important
well haiti is economically just a basket
case i mean the country has just been
devastated
i mean it's a deeply poor country and
the current president of the country
is taking some unconstitutional measures
to try and stay in office
um and the population isn't thrilled
about that uh and
partially they're not thrilled about it
because they feel he's doing this to
continue
his economic austerity right i mean the
living standards in haiti are already
very low
i mean people eat you know eat dirt
mixed with oil i mean i mean the
malnutrition lack of access to health
care it's a deeply impoverished country
you know all kinds of free trade and
and western capitalism has left the
country just underdeveloped
and now we have you know the president
taking an autocratic move and trying to
stay in power
to continue very unpopular economic
policies you know aaron deed was the
leader at one point and
was kind of a precursor of hugo chavez
and bolivarian socialism
he was removed by the united states
there was a u.s military intervention to
remove him
the country has had you know pro-us kind
of leaders for a long time the
economy has gotten worse so now the
population is in rebellion
against this president who's viewed as
kind of an austerity dictator and that's
the situation and us media is of course
you know blocking it out doesn't want
you to know what's happening um i
interviewed reporter danny shaw he was
there he wasn't even able to live stream
on facebook facebook continues blocking
his streams of the protests that are
happening oh my gosh um so
yeah it's worth paying attention to the
situation there because it's again a
population that
was already economically suffering now
you know the pandemic has just wrecked
the place the people are ready to fight
they're in the streets
uh and wall street is very afraid that
you know we could see the rise in haiti
of a new
kind of socialist government like we
have in nicaragua or
in cuba or in venezuela we have only a
minute and a half left but when i was
with the senate
foreign relations committee staff i did
a study on on the haitian economy and
one of the things that i was surprised
to learn
was that the seven largest merchant
families the merchant families that run
the entire
haitian economy are white i
i was fascinated by that yeah i mean i
mean it is particularly shocking
but uh you know the country that you
know was the first slave revolution
uh that you know became a country
essentially because the slaves broke
their chains was the first
black government basically on the on the
western hemisphere
uh the fact that uh that yeah the wealth
is dominated by people of white skin
really shows you how blatant uh the the
neocolonialism is i mean the fact that
they were paying reparations to france
for
hundreds of years for hundreds of years
they were paying reparations to france
for having dared you know win their
freedom and rise up against slavery
uh you know the way haiti has just been
punished for their anti-colonial cast
is pretty horrendous it's pretty
horrendous and it's like
we never learn our lessons uh especially
in our own hemisphere you know there are
so many ways we could have helped the
haitian people
and uh instead we decided to take
advantage of them
uh it's not an accident that haiti is
the poorest
country in the in the western hemisphere
and it's no wonder that
that so many haitians are trying to get
out of their country
to try to save themselves but we will
leave it there
we were happy to be joined today by
michelle witty the co-host of political
misfits
and by journalist and political analyst
caleb maupin thanks to both of them for
coming onto the show today
and thank you for listening join us
again tomorrow
this is the back story
[Music]
you